<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A Briefe request or declaracion presented vnto madame the Duchesse of Parme &amp;c. regente of the Lowe Countrie of Flaunders, by the lordes and nobilitie of the same countrie with the answere and replie, and other writynges / Englished by W.F.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1566</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 35 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 16 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2013-12">2013-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A00921</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 11028</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S2125</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">23060011</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 23060011</idno>
            <idno type="VID">26155</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A00921)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 26155)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1796:3)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A Briefe request or declaracion presented vnto madame the Duchesse of Parme &amp;c. regente of the Lowe Countrie of Flaunders, by the lordes and nobilitie of the same countrie with the answere and replie, and other writynges / Englished by W.F.</title>
                  <author>Margaret, of Austria, Duchess of Parma, 1522-1586.</author>
                  <author>Philip II, King of Spain, 1527-1598.</author>
                  <author>W. F.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[30] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>By Ihon Kyngston, for Thomas Humble, dwellyng at the signe of the George in Lumberdstreate,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Imprinted at London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1566.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Signatures: A-B⁸ (last leaf blank).</note>
                  <note>Imperfect: print show-through.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Lambeth Palace Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Flanders --  Religion --  16th century.</term>
               <term>Netherlands --  History --  Wars of Independence, 1556-1648.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-02</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-02</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-11</date>
            <label>Simon Charles</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-11</date>
            <label>Simon Charles</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:26155:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:26155:1"/>
            <p>¶ A briefe re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſt or declaracion preſented vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to Madame the Ducheſſe of Parme. &amp;c. Regente of the lowe Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trie of Flaunders: By the Lordes and Nobilitie of the ſame Countrie, with the Anſwere and Replie, and other writynges. Engliſhed by W.F. 1566.</p>
            <p>¶ Imprinted at London, by Ihon Kyngſton, for Thomas Humble, dwellyng at the ſigne of the George in Lumberdſtreate.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:26155:2"/>
            <head>To the Reader.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">B</seg>Efore we ſette forthe the declaracion of the Nobi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litie, wee haue thoughte good to expreſſe the co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pie of the letters of Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dame the Ducheſſe of Parme, Regente. &amp;c. ſent to the Gouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nours and Counſaillors Prouinciall of the low Countrie of Flaunders. &amp;c. Alſo the extracte of the letters of the Kyng our ſoueraine lorde, ſent to the Prouin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces of the lowe cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>trie, the whiche haue been publiſhed alredie in ſome places, and are ment to be publiſhed through<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out, whiche thyng hath geuen occaſion to the nobilitie, to preſent the ſaied declaracion, te<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ding to the hin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derance of the execucion of the ſaied letters.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:26155:2"/>
            <div type="letter">
               <head>¶ Margaret by the grace of God Ducheſſe of Parme, and of Plaiſance. &amp;c. Regente and Gouerneſſe.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">R</seg>Ight dere and welbeloued, although that from the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginnyng of the raigne of the Kyng, my Soueraigne Lorde, of the Countries on this ſide, aſwell by the renuyng and pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bliſhyng of the Placardes and ordinau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces of the Emperour Charles, my ſoue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raigne lorde of moſte high memorie de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceaſſed (whom God haue in his glorie) touchyng the ſtate of Religion, ratified and co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>firmed by his royall maieſtie, that the ſame whiche hath ſince béen written you, eue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> at his laſt departure fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> theſaid Countries, for his Kyngdome of Spain, you might alwaies knowe the good zeele and moſte holie affeccion of his ſaid ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ieſtie, to the conſeruacion of our old true faith and catholike Religion, and to the weedyng out of all ſectes and hereſies, in theſe ſaied Countries on this ſide: Not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtandyng this, as it hath pleaſed his ſaid maieſtie for certain occaſions, to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>newe againe vnto vs his moſte holie in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent, by his laſt letters, we haue thought
<pb facs="tcp:26155:3"/> good by expreſſe charge thereof, to repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent that whiche his maieſtie hath writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten vnto vs, whiche is thus in effecte: That his Maieſtie deſiryng nothynge more then the conſeruacion of of theſaid Religion, and of his good ſubiectes on this ſide, in good tranquilitie, peace, vni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, and concorde, and to preſerue them from the inconueniences, whiche haue been ſeen to chaunce in many places of Chriſtendome, for the chaungyng of the ſaied Religion: His ſaied maieſtie wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leth and intendeth, that the ſaid Placar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des and Ordinaunces, of his Imperiall maieſtie deceaſſed and his predeceſſors, be kepte and obſerued in all poinctes, as it is alſo the intent of his ſaied maieſtie, to cauſe to bée well and ſtraitly obſerued that which is decréed by the holie Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cell of Trente, and the Prouinciall con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gregacions, eſpecially as touchyng the reformacion of the Clergie, without re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſtyng the ſaied decrées in any thyng, to the ende that puniſhing the hereſies, the maners alſo maie be corrected: Alſo that all fauour and aſſiſtaunce bée geuen to the Inquiſitors, of the faithe and the ere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cucion of their offices, and that the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiſicion
<pb facs="tcp:26155:3"/> bée made by the ſaied Inquiſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tours, as it hath béen made heretofore, and as apperteineth to them by diuine and humain right, the whiche thyng his Maieſtie alſo expreſſely commaundeth, by his ſaied letters. And folowyng this writyng of his ſaid maieſte, and to obey therevnto, in a thyng ſo holy and fauou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable, we could not omitte to write this vnto you, for to praie you, require you, and of the behalfe of his ſaied maieſtie to commaunde you very expreſſely, to call and guide your ſelues herein, accordyng to the ordinaunce of his ſaid Maieſtie, without gainſtandyng it in any poyncte or article, and that you cauſe theſame to be vnderſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ded to the officers, and thoſe of the lawe, of the principall Tounes of the Countrie and Countie of <gap reason="illegible: omitted in print" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> to thende that thei maie order theim ſel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ues thereafter, without diſſimulacion or couine, vnder the penalties conteined in the ſame Placardes. And ſo moche the better to haue knowledge of it, that ye appoincte and aſſigne a Councellour of your Colledge (who notwithſtandyng maie be chaunged from half yere to half yere, to thende that one alone be not al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>waies
<pb facs="tcp:26155:4"/> charged) and he to doe none other thyng, but to haue regarde to the ſaied Countrie of <gap reason="illegible: omitted in print" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> for the obſerua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cion of the decrées of theſaid holy Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cell, and to aduertiſe you alwaies of that whiche ſhalbée needefull to bée prouided for, accordyng to the intente of his ſaied maieſtie. And to the ende that wé maie alwaies knowe the ſtate of the ſaied Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion, as is aforeſaied, wee deſire and commaunde you as aforſaied, that from thrée monethes to thrée monethes, ye write vnto vs the ſucceſſe particularly, makyng your recourſe to vs in matters of difficultée, or to them of the priuie counſaill of his ſaid maieſtie, that report maie be made vnto vs, wheras likewiſe we will appoinct ſome Councellor, who ſhall take the charge particularly, and ſhall conferre with you, and hym that ſhalbe ſent by you. And to the ende that vppon all this afore ſaied, you might ſo moche the better ſe the expreſſe pleaſure of his ſaied maieſtie, wée haue cauſed to bee ioyned herevnto, the chief poinctes of the letters and other writynges of his ſaied maieſtie, concernyng this matter, to the ende to order and guide your ſel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ues,
<pb facs="tcp:26155:4"/> accordyng to the forme and tenour of theſame without defaulte. And thus moſte deare and welbeloued, the Lorde haue you in his kepyng.</p>
               <closer>
                  <dateline>Written at Bruſſells <date>the .xviii. daie of December. <hi>Anno Dn<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>i .1565. H. Vt</hi>
                     </date> 
                  </dateline>
                  <signed>vnderneth was written <hi>Margarita.</hi> And lower then that the Seale of Ouerlope.</signed> Vpon the backe was moreouer written, to our right deare and welbeloued, the Preſident and people of the Counſell of the kyng in.</closer>
            </div>
            <div type="extract">
               <head>¶ An extract of the laſt letters and writynges ſent by the Kyng to Madame the Du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cheſſe, with the laſt diſpatche, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cernyng the ſtate of Religion.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">F</seg>irſt of all, as concernyng the Placardes and Ordinaunces aſwell old as newe, touchyng theſaid ſtate of Religion, that his Maieſtie vnderſtandyng the eſtate wherein the affaires of Religion nowe ſtand on this ſide, it is not conuenient to make, as touchyng the ſaied Placardes and Ordinaunces any chaunge, but that the ſaied Placardes of the Emperours Maieſtie deceaſſed, and thoſe of his ſaied Maieſtie be alſo executed. And his Maie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtie
<pb facs="tcp:26155:5"/> hath perceiued the cauſe of the euill which hath chaunced, and of that it is ſo augmented &amp; gone ſo farre, to haue béen by the negligence, ſlouthfulneſſe, and diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſimulacion of the Iudges. And that if there be any Iudges, whiche dare not or will not execute them, for fear of any tu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mult, then let his Maieſtie thereof haue knowledge, to the ende that he maie pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uide other of ſtouter harte &amp; better zeale, to the excucion thereof, wherof there can be no default in thoſe ſaied Countries, ſeyng there be ſo many Catholikes, and men deſirous to ſerue God and his Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ieſtie, and that doyng this, and executing theſaied Placardes, it is to be hoped that by that meanes, the hurt whiche is doen maie be the better and ſoner remedied.</p>
               <p>For the ſeconde, as concernyng that whiche toucheth the Inquiſitours of the faithe, his Maieſtie chargeth her high<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, to helpe that theſaied Inquiſitours bée fauoured in that, which toucheth the execucion and adminiſtracion of their charge, in aſmoche as is conuenient for the profite and ſuſtentacion of the Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion, beyng thintent of his Maieſtie, that theſaied Inquiſicion be made by theſaid
<pb facs="tcp:26155:5"/> Inquiſitours, as it hath béen vntill this tyme, and as to the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> belongeth by diuine and humaine right, and that this is no newe thyng, ſeyng that it hath been al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>waies doen ſo in the tyme of the Empe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rours Maieſtie deceaſſed, and of his ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ieſtie alſo. The inconueniences whiche are to bee feared, beyng moche more ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paraunt, more nigh, and greater, when there is not prouiſion made for the ſaied Inquiſitors, of that whiche apperteineth to their office, and that thei are not aſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſted. And becauſe her highnes doeth vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtande what this importeth, his Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ieſtie chargeth her as moche as ſhe maie to doe whatſoeuer ſhalbe neceſſary ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vnto, and that ſhe doe not conſente, that any other thing be intreated of, her high<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe knowyng how moche his Maieſtie hath the harte, deſire, and contented that it ſhall thus bee.</p>
               <p>For the third, his Maieſtie commau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth her highnes, that ſeyng that the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie Councell of Trent was alredy publi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed, that there reſted nothyng but that whiche toucheth the execucion, whiche belongeth to the Biſhops, her highneſſe ſhould cauſe them to make all ſpede and
<pb facs="tcp:26155:6"/> aſſiſtance poſſible, to thende that ſhe en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>force her ſelf as behoueth. Alſo that the ſame be executed, whiche the ſaid Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cell of Trente hath decreed, as concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning the reformacion of the life and ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners of the ſpiritualtie, his maieſtie char<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>gyng as well her highneſſe, as the offi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cers of his ſaied Maieſtie, to geue all the fauour and encouragyng that ſhould be néedefull, and that if in caſe it ſhould bée requiſite, that on the behalf of his Maie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtie, ſhe ſhould cauſe it to bee diſpatchte quickly, eſpecially where the people of the Churche, will not obeye to the refor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>macion made by the Biſhops, conforma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to the decrée of theſaied Councell of Trente.</p>
               <p>And for concluſion, ſithe that whiche his Maieſtie writeth to her highneſſe, as is aforſaied, is that whiche belongeth to the profite of the Religion &amp; of the coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trie on this ſide, whiche were nothynge worthe without theſame, and that this is the waie for to keepe them in Iuſtice, peace, and tranquilitie. And becauſe her highnes ſéeth what it importeth, his ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ieſtie requireth her againe to folowe the waie, whereby that whiche is aforeſaied,
<pb facs="tcp:26155:6"/> maie be brought to effect, &amp; that it ſhalbe the thing, wherby his Maieſtie maie re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue moche contentacion, aſwell of her highneſſe, as of the Lordes beyng vnder her, to whom her highneſſe ſhould geue in charge theſame, to the ende that thei imploſe themſelues as his Maieſtie tru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteth that thei will not faile, knowyng the contentment that thei ſhal doe vnto him, beſides that thei ſhal fulfill the due<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie of ſoche perſonages as thei be, and ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cordyng to the obligacion that thei haue to the ſeruice of God, and of his maieſtie and to the vniuerſall profit of the coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trey on this ſide, and alſo of theim ſelues perticularly.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="statement">
               <head>¶ The Preſident and Councell of the Kynges ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ieſtie of Hollande, Zelande, and Frieſlande.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">N</seg>Oble, worthie, and diſcrete, and alſo good frendes, we haue recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued certaine letters of the Du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches, Regent of the Kynges Maieſtie in theſe lowe countries, with expreſs;e com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion and commaundement vnto your honors. For to certifie how his maieſtie, nothing in the world more doeth require then the conſeruacion of the Catholike religion, and his good ſubiectes of theſe
<pb facs="tcp:26155:7"/> countries in good peace, reſte, quietneſſe and vnion to maintaine, and theſame to kepe fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> all inconueniences, the whiche in many places of Chriſtendome, by the chaungyng of religion, be chaunſed and happened: Doeth will you to vnderſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>de that the Proclamacions and ordinau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ces of the late Imperiall maieſtie, made vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> poinctes of religion to be kept, and in all poinctes to be mainteined and executed, as alſo the minde of his maieſtie is well and ſtraightly to maintain that, whiche by the holy &amp; generall Councell of Tre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t by the Prouinciall ſynodes hath béen or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deined and ſtatuted, and in eſpeciall as touchyng the reformacion of the Spiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tualtie, without any thyng againſte the ſame, to doe that in correctyng of the he<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſies, euill maners, by theſame maie be amended and puniſhed: Therefore his maieſtie doeth will that the Inquiſitors of the faithe, in the executyng and exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſyng of their office, ſhall haue all the helpe and aſſiſtance that you are able to ſhewe or do vnto them: and that the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiſicio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> by the ſame Inquiſitors be doen in like ſort, as it hath béen vnto this pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent tyme, accordyng as it apperteineth
<pb facs="tcp:26155:7"/> vnto them, by Spirituall and Temporal lawes, the whiche his Maieſtie expreſſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly hath commaunded, and in theſame to his Maieſtie, in ſo holy &amp; good a matter to be obedient, we could no leſſe do, then to write theſe preſentes, and in theſame to require, and in the name of his Maie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtie to commau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>de very earneſtly, that in theſe you will dooe, accordyng vnto the will &amp; ordinaunces of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>is maieſtie, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out doyng, or ſuffring to be doen againſt theſame in any poincte, vpon paine and penaltie of the Placarde and ordinance comprehended, like as by vs hath béen in the departyng of his maieſtie out of this lowe Countree, by his maieſtie at large hath béen writte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. You ſhall further kepe and obſerue the laſte Proclamacion, pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bliſhed the <hi>.29.</hi> daie of Marche afore Ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter. <hi>Anno .1563.</hi> touching the Midwifes with alſo that that hath been co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ded you by our letters miſſiues, at y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſending of theſame proclamacion, as to kepe and take good regard vpon al ſuche as do ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent themſelues fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the churche, not hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting Maſſe vpon the Sondaie &amp; holy day in that his Maieſties letters, the <hi>.29.</hi> daie of Marche <hi>Anno .1563.</hi> and ours the <hi>11</hi> of
<pb facs="tcp:26155:8"/> Aprill. <hi>An 1564.</hi> after Eaſter, &amp; vnto vs. Certified that daily more and more, vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the ſtretes, wagons, boates, and ſhippes, and other places, diſhoneſt &amp; vnreuerent ſonges he vſed againſt the holie Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentes of the Altar, Baptiſme, and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers: We charge &amp; ordein your honore, theſame co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ming vnto your knowledge, with all comely maner, theſame to let &amp; hinder, and thoſe to apprehend that ſhall ſyng any ſuche Songes, contrary to the chriſten faith, vnto the tenour of his ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ieſties Proclamacion aforeſaied, and to the intent that you, and alſo all the ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iectes, the better ordein your ſelues, vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the good pleaſure and will of his ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ieſties Proclamacion: you ſhall hence<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forthe take better regarde, that the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clamacion vpon the poinctes of Religio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> namely the Proclamacion of the yere of our Lorde <hi>.1556.</hi> euery halfe yere bee re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nued and publiſhed, to thende that ſuche as bee enclined to any newe learnyng and ſectes, by the penaltie in the Procla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>macio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> conteined, might be retired.</p>
               <closer>
                  <salute>Noble worthie, diſcrete, &amp; in eſpeciall good frendes, our lorde God be with you:</salute>
                  <dateline>writte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> at y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Hage <date>the 8 of Ianuary. 1565. Stilo curi.</date>
                  </dateline>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div type="proposition">
               <pb facs="tcp:26155:8"/>
               <head>¶ The Propoſicion made by Mounſire de Brede<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rode, to Madame the Ducheſſe, before he preſented the declaracion.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">M</seg>Adame, the gentlemen aſſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled in this toune, and others of like qualitie in compitente no<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ber, who for certain reſpec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes, are not here preſent, haue ſtaied for the ſeruice of the kyng, and the publike weale of this lowe Countrie, to preſent vnto your highneſſe with all humilitie, this declaracion, vpon the whiche it ſhal pleaſe you to geue ſoche order, as ſhalbée thought conuenient, humbly beſechyng your highneſſe, to take it in good parte. And further Madam, we are aduertiſed to haue been charged before your high<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, before the lordes of the Councell, and others, that this our deliberacion, hath chiefly béen made for to raiſe vp tu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>multes, vprores &amp; ſedicions, and, whiche is more abhominable, thei haue charged vs that we would chaunge our Prince, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>auyng practiſes, leagues; and conſpira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies, with Princes &amp; Capttaines ſtraun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers, aſwell Frenchemen, Almaines, as others, whiche thyng we neuer thought <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>pon; and is altogether contrary to our
<pb facs="tcp:26155:9"/> loyaltie, and to that whiche your high<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes ſhall finde by this declaracion: beſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chyng neuertheleſſe your highneſſe, to name and diſcouer vnto vs, theim that haue ſo vniuſtly blamed ſo noble and honourable a company.</p>
               <p>Moreouer Madame, the Lordes here preſent haue vnderſtandyng, that there is ſome emongeſt them, who perticular<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly are accuſed and charged, to haue ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken in hande and gone about, to bryng to effecte the forſaied wicked enterpriſe, aſwell with Frenchmen, as other ſtrau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers, whereat we feele our ſelues great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly greued. And therefore humbly beſech your highneſſe and fauor, as to name the ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſars, and accuſed, to the ende that the wronge and miſchief beyng diſcouered, your highneſſe maie make brief and ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifeſt Iuſtice, and by that meanes ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſe the euilles and ſlaunders, whiche might come vpon it, beyng well aſſured that your highnes will neuer ſuffer, that ſoche a noble and honourable company, ſhould remaine charged, with ſo greate infamies and wicked actes.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="petition">
               <pb facs="tcp:26155:9"/>
               <head>¶ The requeſt of the Nobilitie of the lowe Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trie, preſented to Madame the Ducheſſe of Parme and Plaiſance. &amp;c.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">M</seg>Adame, it is well enough knowe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that throughout all Chriſte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dome hath alwaies been greatlie re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nowmed (as it is yet at this preſente) the greate fidelitie of the people of this lowe Countrie, to wardes their lordes and na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turall Princes, wherin the nobilitie hath alwaies kept the chief ra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cke, as theſame whiche hath neuer ſpared neither bodie nor goodes, for the conſeruacion and en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſe of the greatneſſe of theim. In the whiche we the moſte humble ſubiectes of his maieſtie will alwaies continue from good to better, ſo that bothe daie &amp; night we kepe our ſelues redie, for to doe hym moſt humble ſeruice, bothe with our bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies and goodes: and ſeyng in what caſe the affaires are at this preſente, haue thought beſte to charge our ſelues with ſome ill will, then to keepe ſecrete from your highneſſe, thynges whiche might hereafter tourne to the preiudice of his maieſtie, and forthwith altogether trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble the reſt and tranquilitie of this coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trie. Truſtyng that theffecte will appere
<pb facs="tcp:26155:10"/> in tyme, that emongeſte all the ſeruices which we might haue doen, or hereafter maie do to his maieſtie, this ſame ought to be accompted emongeſt the moſte no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table, and to beſt purpoſe, whereby wée aſſuredly perſwade our ſelues, that your highnes can not take it but in very good part. Although then, Madame, that wee doubte not but that all that, whiche his maieſtie hath heretofore, and alſo nowe preſently of newe doeth conſtitute, tou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chyng the Inquiſicion and ſtraite obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uacion of the Placardes for the ſtate of religion, hath had ſome foundacion and iuſte title, to wit, to continue that which the Emperor Charles, of moſt high me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>morie deceſſed, had eſtabliſhed for a good intente. Neuertheleſſe conſideryng that the difference of one time from an other, bryngeth immediatly with it diuerſitie of remedies, and that now of late within theſe fewe yeres theſaied Placarde, not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtandyng that thei were not execu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted with all rigour, haue neuertheleſſe giuen occaſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to many greuous inco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niences. Certainly the laſt reſolucion of his maieſtie, by the whiche he forbad not onely that theſaid Placardes ſhould not
<pb facs="tcp:26155:10"/> be mitigated, but alſo plainly commau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, that the Inquiſion ſhould bee obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued, and the Placardes executed with all rigour, doeth geue vs ſufficient iuſte oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſion to feare, that therby not onely the ſaied inconueniences ſhould greatly en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſe, but alſo that in thende ſhould fo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowe a commotion and generall ſedicio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, tendyng to the miſerable ruine of the whole countrie, accordyng as the mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſt tokens of the alteracion of the people (whiche nowe appeareth on euery ſide) doeth geue vs plainly to vnderſtande.</p>
               <p>Wherfore, knowyng the euidencie &amp; greatneſſe of the daunger, whiche doeth threaten vs, haue hitherto hoped y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> either by the lordes, or by theſtates of the coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trée, declaracion ſhould be made in con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t time vnto your highnes, to thend to remedie it, by taking awaie the cauſe &amp; originall of the euill: but ſince hauyng ſéen, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> thei haue not executed it for ſome occaſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to vs vnknowen, and that in the meane while the euill encreaſeth daily, in ſomoche y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> the danger of ſedicion &amp; ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerall rebellio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> is euen at hand, we haue thought it good, folowing y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> othe of fideli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie &amp; homage together, with y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> good will y<hi rend="sup">t</hi>
                  <pb facs="tcp:26155:11"/> we beare to his maieſtie and the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trie, not to tary and longer, but rather to ſet forthe our ſelues with the firſte, to do the duetie required, and ſo moche the more boldly, becauſe wee haue more oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſion to truſt that his maieſtie will take our aduertiſement in very good part, ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yng that the matter toucheth be nerer, then it doeth any other, ſeyng that wee are in more daunger of the inconueni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ences and calamities, whiche cuſtoma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly come of ſoche like accide<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tes, hauing for the moſte part our houſes and goodes ſcituate in the fieldes, and readie to be a praie to euery man: conſideryng alſo ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerally, that folowyng the rigour of the ſaied Placardes, as his maieſtie hath ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſly co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>maunded to procede, there ſhall not bee emongeſt vs any man, no nor in the whole countrie on this ſide, of what eſtate or condicio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſoeuer he be, that ſhall not bee founde giltie of the confiſcation and forfeicture of his bodie and goodes, and ſubiecte to the reproche of the firſte enemie, who to haue parte of the confiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation, will accuſe hym vnder colour of the Placardes, not hauyng any other thyng left hym for refuge, but onely the
<pb facs="tcp:26155:11"/> diſſimulacion of the officer, into whoſe mercie his life &amp; goodes are wholly put. In conſideracion whereof, wee haue ſo moche the more occaſion, moſte humbly to beſeche your highnes (as in deede we beſeche you by this preſent requeſte) for to geue good order herein. And (for the importaunce of the matter) to ſende as ſpedely as maie bee, an expreſſe and fitte manne to his maieſtie to aduertiſe hym, and beſeche hym moſte humbly on our behalfe, that it would pleaſe hym to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uide as well for the tyme preſent, as the tyme to come. And foraſmoche as the ſame can not be doen, ſuffryng theſaied Placardes to remaine in their force, ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yng that thereof dependeth the ſprynge, and originall of the ſaied inconuenien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces: that it would pleaſe hym to aboliſhe theſame, the whiche ſhalbe nedefull for the withſtandyng of the totall ruine and loſſe of all his countries on this ſide.</p>
               <p>And to thende that his maieſtie haue no occaſion to thinke that wee (whiche pretende nothyng but to doe hym moſte humble obedience) would take in hande to bridle hym, or make hym a Lawe at our pleaſure (as wee doubte not but our
<pb facs="tcp:26155:12"/> aduerſaries will interprete it for our diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aduantage) it maie pleaſe his maieſtie, to make other Ordinaunces, by the ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiſe and conſent of all the eſtate general<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly aſſembled, to the ende to forſée to this aforeſaied, by other meanes more apte and conuenient, and without ſo euident daungers. Beſechyng alſo moſte hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly his highneſſe, that vntill ſoche tyme that his maieſtie ſhal attende to our iuſt requeſt, and geue order accordyng to his good and iuſt pleaſure, that in the meane tyme he forſee vnto the ſaied daungers, by a generall ſtaie, aſwell of the Inqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſicion, as of all execucion of theſaid Pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cardes, vntill ſoche tyme that his maie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtie haue taken other order.</p>
               <p>Proteſtyng expreſly, that in aſmoche as to vs apparteineth, wée are acquited of our duetie by this preſente aduertiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mente: Sith that from henceforthe, wée diſcharge our ſelues before God and me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, declaryng, that if any inconuenience, diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>order, ſedicion, rebellion, or ſheddyng of blood, do hereafter come to paſſe, through faulte that there hath not been remedy taken in tyme, we can not be blamed for kepyng cloſe ſo apparant an euill, wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in
<pb facs="tcp:26155:12"/> wée take God, the Kyng, your high<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, and the Lordes of his Counſell, to gether and our conſcience in witneſſe, that we haue proceded as behoueth good and lawfull ſeruitors, and faithfull ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iectes of the Kyng, not exceadyng in any thyng the limites of our duetie, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore alſo wee ſo moche the more inſtant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly beſeche, that your highneſſe will ſee vnto it, before that the euill happen.</p>
               <closer>
                  <dateline>Preſented by Mounſire Henry of Brederode, Lorde of the ſaid place, with Lodewicke Erie of Naſſowe therles of Berge and Culenborgh accompanied with the Nobilitie of the lowe Countrie,
<date>the <hi>.5.</hi> of Aprill <hi>1565.</hi> before Eaſter.</date>
                  </dateline>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div type="answer">
               <head>¶ The Anſwere made in the Counſell of Eſtate, by Madame. &amp;c. vpon the declaracion goyng before.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">H</seg>Er highneſſe, hauyng vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanded, what is required and domaunded, by the matters conteined in this requeſte, is fully determined to ſende towardes the Kynges maisſtie, for to preſente it vnto hym, and to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſe towardes hym all good meanes, that her highneſſe ſhall thynke,
<pb facs="tcp:26155:13"/> may ſerue to diſpoſe and encline his ſai<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Maieſtie, to condiſcende to the requeſt of theſaied ſuppliantes, who ought not to doubt, but that all thynges ſhalbée wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy and conformable to his natiue and accuſtomed benignitie: her highnes ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uyng alredy (before the commyng of the ſaied ſuppliantes, by the aſſiſtaunce and aduiſe of the gouernours of the Prouin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, Knightes of the Order, and thoſe of the Councell, beyng vnder her) gone a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout to conceiue and addreſſe, a modera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cion of the ſaid Placardes, touchyng the ſtate of Religion, for to preſente it vnto his ſaied maieſtie. The whiche modera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cion her highnes hopeth ſhould be found ſoche, that it ſhould geue to euery one reaſonable contentment. And ſeing that thaucthoritie of her highnes, as the ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pliantes maie well conſider and vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand, doeth not extende ſo farre, as to be able to ſtay the Inquiſicion, and the Pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cardes as thei demaunde, and that it be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>houeth not to leaue the countrie, as tou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chyng religion without lawe, her high<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe truſteth that the ſuppliantes will content them ſelues with this, that ſhe ſende (to the ende aforſaid) towardes the
<pb facs="tcp:26155:13"/> kynges maieſtie, and in the meane tyme whileſt ſhe waiteth for his anſwere, her highnes will geue order, that aſwell by the Inquiſitors (wherof there haue béen vntill nowe) that by the officers whiche haue the ouerſight, thynges be executed diſcretly, and modeſtly, as apperteineth to their charges, in ſoche ſorte that there bee no occaſion geuen of complainte, her highnes truſtyng alſo, that the ſupplian<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes will order themſelues after ſoche fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhion, that it ſhall not be nedefull to vſe it otherwiſe. And it is to bee hoped that by the good meanes, whiche her hignes ſhall make to his maieſtie, he ſhalbe con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent to diſcharge the other of the Inqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſicion where ſhe is, accordyng as it maye be vnderſtanded, that it is now declared vpon the requeſte of the chief tounes of Brabant, that thei ſhall not bée charged with it. And her highnes will labour ſo moche the more fréely towardes his ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ieſtie, to the ende and effect aforeſaied, in that ſhe is aſſured that the ſuppliauntes doe minde and intende determinatly, to bryng in no newe thyng, contrary to the auncient religion, obſerued in the coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trée on this ſide, but to mainteine it and
<pb facs="tcp:26155:14"/> obſerue it with all their power.</p>
               <closer>
                  <dateline>Made by her highnes at Bruſels, <date>the <hi>6.</hi> daie of Aprill <hi>.1565.</hi> before Eaſter.</date>
                  </dateline>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div type="reply">
               <head>¶ The Replie vpon the Anſwere goyng be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore made the. <hi>8.</hi> daie of Aprill.</head>
               <p>MAdame, hauyng ſéen the aun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer, which it hath pleaſed your highnes to geue vs, we will not faile firſt of all to thancke moſte humbly your highneſſe, for the briefe expedicion thereof, eſpecially of the ſatiſfaccion that your highneſſe hath had of this our aſſe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, the whiche was made for none other occaſion, but for the good ſeruice of the kinges maieſtie, &amp; the tranquilitie of the countrie: And for the better contentme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, and reſt of the ſame Countrée, wee haue greatly deſired that the ſaied aunſwere of your highneſſe, had been made more ample and plainer. Neuertheleſſe, ſithe that your highnes hath not the aucthori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie that we deſired, as wée vnderſtande, whereof we are very ſory, wee truſte ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cordyng to the hope and aſſuraunce that your highneſſe hath geuen vs, that there ſhalbee ſoche order made, aſwell towar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des the Magiſtrates, as the Inquiſitors, enioynyng them to ſtaie themſelues fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <pb facs="tcp:26155:14"/> all ſutes proceadyng of the Inquiſicion, Ordinaunces, or Placardes, aſwell old, as newe, touchyng the ſtate of Religion, vntill the Kynges Maieſtie haue other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe detreed. Of our parte, Madame, ſith that we deſire nothyng but to folowe all that whiche by his maieſtie, with the ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiſe and conſent of the Eſtates general<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly aſſembled ſhalbe decreed, for the main<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>teinyng of the aunciente Religion, wee truſt to gide our ſelues in ſoche ſort, that your highneſſe ſhall haue no occaſion of miſcontentment. And if any man co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mit any hainous or ſedicious acte, that he be by your highnes, and them of the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cell to Eſtate, appoincted ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>ke puniſhe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, as the deſert of the deede ſhall re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quire. Proteſtyng againe that if any in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conuenience doe riſe, by faulte of not ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uyng geuen good order, that wee haue fulfilled our duetie, moſte humbly beſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chyng your highnes to hold that our du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie as agreable and bounden, receiuyng it for the ſeruice of his Maieſtie. Offring our ſelues to remain moſte humble and obediente ſeruitours to your highneſſe: and to dye at his feete for his ſeruice, as oft as it ſhall pleaſe your highnes to co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maunde
<pb facs="tcp:26155:15"/> vs.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="petition">
               <head>¶ Requeſtes of the fower members of Flanders, and the Cities, and Caſſellries ioynyng thereunto vpon the effecte of Inquiſicion.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">S</seg>Hewyng and requiryng in all humilitie, the fower members of your countrée and Counteſſe of Flanders, as well for them as for all the Citées, Caſſellries in generall of all the Inhabiters, and Subiectes of the ſame Countrees. How that not long ſithens, thei had preſented your Maieſtie a ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plicacion, for that it might pleaſe your highnes, to permitte the ſuppliantes, to emoy in the afore written qualitie, their old libertie and freedome, for the preſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uacion of them, and to forbidde the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiſitours, and other Spirituall perſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes, for the bryngyng in of any newe matters, through the practiſe of Inqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſicion, and that vpon the afore written ſupplicacion, as it nothyng had been or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deined. For that your maieſtie firſte and formoſte require in perticular, to vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtande the meanyng of the ſuppliantes, accordyng to ſupplicacions here vnto an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nered, ſo is it that thei for the ſatiſfaccio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, thei nowe adreſſyng them ſelues vnto
<pb facs="tcp:26155:15"/> your Maieſtie, as to the ſame perforſed by obligacion of their othe, and to the conſeruacion and welfare, of your afore written lowe Countrées: as alſo newly thervnto moued, through the newe prac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſe and ſubteltie of my Lorde the Biſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhoppe of Bridgis, and of miaſter Peter Litelman, them namyng Inquiſitours, as it appereth by the copie of the articles by them, ſhewyng herevnto annexed. Therefore requiryng very humbly, that you takyng regarde, vpon the reaſons hereby rehearſed at large, by the afore ſaied ſupplicacion, and in eſpeciall that your patrimoniall landes, their neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bours not brought to bondage or ſubiec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cion, of the aforeſaied Inquiſicion, by li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bertie of the whiche, your other patre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moniall Countrées, the Inhabitours of the afore written, your countrée of Fla<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders, ſhould be occaſioned to depart, and to leaue their Countrée and landes, for the auoydyng of ſoche bondage, vexacio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> and ſubieccion, as alredy hath béen fou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d by experience. It maie pleaſe your Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ieſtie, to let the ſuppliantes enioy peace<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ably the aforeſaied, their rightes, frée<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>domes, cuſtomes, and vſaunces, and for
<pb facs="tcp:26155:16"/> as moche as the exerciſe of the aforeſaid Inquiſicion, is directly contrary to al the aforeſaied rightes, freedome, cuſtomes, and vſances of the ſaied ſuppliantes: the ſame wholy to diſanull, and wholy to fruſtrate and make voide, in aſmoche as it toucheth the temporall perſones. For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>biddyng furthermore all Spirituall Iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtices, to take any knowlege of matters belongyng vnto the knowledge of tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porall iuriſdiccion, but theſame to putte onely to the iudgement of the Temporal Iudges. And not to conſent that the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>habiters of your afore written countrees of Flanders, more ſtraightly to be bou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d to any inquiſite or rigour of Ordinaun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces and Proclamacions, made touchyng Religio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, then other their ioynyng coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trees and Prouinces, the aforeſaied de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claracions Your maieſtie well aſſuring that thei of your countrée of Flanders, and the Commons in generall, hauyng no other meanyng or deſire, then them ſelues to employe, &amp; to the countrée ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, and mainteinyng of the old catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like faithe, &amp; to al the ſeruice of your ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ieſtie, as true and obediente ſubiectes of theſame.</p>
               <closer>
                  <dateline>
                     <date>
                        <hi>anno .1565.</hi> April after Eaſter.</date>
                  </dateline>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:26155:16"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
